SAMUEL ANGILA OLUNG'ATI

Quality Assurance & Control Professional

samuelangila.o@gmail.com +254 725 622 026

Career Summary

I am a professional whose area of expertise is in food production, food safety & analysis, inspection, client service and satisfaction, communication, laboratory analysis, product development and has an extensive knowledge in the food industry.

I have over 10 years of professional experience which spreads across food industrial and distribution network, quality, safety and assurance sector with a proven track record in successful strategy development and implementation, food internal auditing, business development and control gained from working in various companies.

Core Competencies

Skills

Food Safety Management | Internal Audits | Product Tests and Analysis | Research | Training | Staff Support |
Procurement | Communication Skills | Team Leadership & Supervision | Customer Engagement and Satisfaction |
Record Keeping | Troubleshooting | Organization | Time Management | Stock Controls | Performance Management
| Company Safety Compliance | Company Liaison | ERP Management

Technical SkillsMicrosoft Suite: Word, PowerPoint & Excel | HACCP

Work History

QUALITY MANAGEMENT SYSTEMS ADMINISTRATOR – Pressmaster Africa Ltd | Nairobi (Current)

Pressmaster Africa Ltd (a part of Ramco Group) is a print and packaging manufacturer that provides a wide product range using various types of paper and board.

Key Responsibilities

- o Development of the food safety management system for ISO 22000:2018 certification.
- EHS coordination.

CHIEF OPERATIONS OFFICER - Moringa for Life EPZ Ltd | Kwale (November 2020 - March 2021)

Moringa for Life EPZ Ltd is a company that deals with the organic farming of Moringa oleifera and processing of food supplements, herbal infusions and spice blends from the same for local and export markets.

Key Responsibilities

- Developing and overseeing the implementation of operational policies for departments.
- Coordinating and monitoring the implementation of Quality management, Environmental,
 Occupational Safety and Health management, Food safety management, Sustainable Agriculture (Rainforest and Organic farming) and Fair for Life systems.
- o Production planning and coordination.

TECHNICAL MANAGER - Subati Group Ltd | Makueni (February 2020 - November 2020)

Subati Group Ltd is a grower and exporter of over 100 varieties of spray and single head roses and 15 types of herbs.

Key Responsibilities

- Quality Management: Coordinating and monitoring the implementation of Food Safety management, Environmental, Occupational Safety and Health management and Good Agricultural Practices.
- **Company Compliance:** Validate and assure compliance with established food safety and quality objectives through monitoring programs and team supervision.
- **Staff Training:** Planning staff training within all departments to ensure understanding of standards, specifications and job requirements.

Key Accomplishments

- Successfully led the company through GlobalGAP, GRASP, TESCO-NURTURE, F2F, BRCGS and ETI re-certification processes.
- Actively worked to streamline hygiene protocols at the Production and Processing levels.
- Led in the implementation of measures that helped reduce customer complaints by 50% within 7 months.

HEAD OF COMPLIANCE, QUALITY AND LABORATORY – Live Love Well EPZ Ltd | Kwale (Dec 2018 – Feb 2019) Live Love Well EPZ Ltd is a company that deals with the organic farming and processing of Moringa for the export market.

Skills acquired

Project preparation and planning, Operative planning, Goal setting, Decision making, Capacity planning, Lean management.

Key responsibility

Coordinating and monitoring the implementation of Quality management, Environmental, Occupational Safety and Health management, Food safety management, Sustainable Agriculture (Rainforest and Organic farming) systems.

CERTIFICATIONS MANAGER - Moringa for Life EPZ Ltd | Msambweni (January 2016 - November 2018)

Moringa for Life EPZ Ltd is a company that deals with the organic farming of Moringa oleifera and processing of food supplements, herbal infusions and spice blends from the same for local and export markets.

Key Responsibilities

- Quality Management:
 - Coordinating and monitoring the implementation of Quality management, Environmental,
 Occupational Safety and Health management, Food safety management, Sustainable Agriculture (Rainforest and Organic farming) systems.
 - Coordinating laboratory activities to ensure they meet the demand of quality assurance for the products.
 - o Production planning and coordination
- Company Compliance: Liaised with local and international regulatory and certification bodies such as KEBS,
 KEPHIS and ECOCERT for inquiries and inspections. Application for relevant certificates of operation statutory compliance and exports.
- **Staff Training:** Conduct Food Safety and Quality training programs to all employees with emphasis on continuous improvement.
- Team Leadership & Supervision: Support the QA and Food Safety team in undertaking root causes and

corrective actions from customer complaints and/or system failures and implement the corrective actions with the plant operations team.

Key Accomplishments

- Successfully led the company through ISO 22000:2005, KOSHER and HALAL certification processes
- Actively worked as part of a team to streamline hygiene protocols at the Processing facility and Warehouse as well as Occupational Health and Safety requirements.

RESEARCH & DEVELOPMENT OFFICER – Moringa for Life EPZ Ltd | Msambweni (March 2014 – Dec 2015)

Moringa for Life EPZ Ltd is a company that deals with the organic farming of Moringa oleifera and processing of food supplements, herbal infusions and spice blends from the same for local and export markets.

Key Responsibilities

- Quality Assurance:
 - o Managed quality control and quality assurance operations at the Laboratory and Factory.
 - Establishment of the in-house laboratory for the quality assurance of ingredients, online and finished products.
- **Procurement:** Managed the procurement of laboratory equipment from the initial stages of determining laboratory tests to be conducted to sourcing for suppliers.
- **Product Tests:** Liaised with a laboratory services provider to carry out tests on the soil, manure and test products.
- Company Liaison:
 - Liaised with the Farm Manager about Organic farming certification process documentation and correspondence with the certifying body.
 - Liaised with external service providers-Laboratories, Regulatory bodies and consultants, that offered auxiliary services to the firm.

Key Accomplishments

- o I was the management representative in charge of ISO 9001:2008 implementation and certification.
- o I led the company through a successful ISO 9001:2008 certification process.
- Worked as part of the team that led to the achievement of Organic certification, Rainforest Alliance (SAN) certification and KEBS Standard Mark of Quality.
- Led the research and development new products (food supplements) for the market.

LABORATORY ANALYST | TECHNICIAN – James Finlay (K) Ltd | Kericho (2010 – 2014)

Saosa Factory (Tea Extracts Division) is an automated, black and green Instant tea manufacturing plant that is ISO 22000 certified.

Key Responsibilities

- Product Tests & Analysis:
 - Undertook all requisite testing of raw materials, finished products and any external samples that require testing using HPLC, GC, UV-visible spectrophotometer and other appropriate instruments.
 - Assisted in coordinating all requisite QA testing of raw materials and packaging materials.
 - Worked with QA assistant in carrying out internal investigation for all analytical and product nonconformances.
 - o Participated in the development of analytical methods and standard operating procedures.
 - o Participated in internal and external laboratory ring tests (inter-lab comparison of analyses).
- Lab Maintenance: Ensured laboratory instruments are maintained and calibrated as required.

Key Accomplishments

- Worked to ensure health and safety regulations are adhered to, and that there was compliance to all the existing accreditations in the plant i.e. GLP, ISO 17025, and ISO 22000.
- Participated in new product development trials.

Education

Academic Training

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE | Analytical Chemistry – Jomo Kenyatta University of Agriculture and Technology (2003-2007)

KENYA CERTIFICATE OF SECONDARY EDUCATION – Musingu High School (1999-2001)

COMPUTER & BASIC PROGRAMMING – Kima Mission School | Jomo Kenyatta University of Agriculture and

Technology (2002-2004)

Professional Training

ISO/IEC 17025:2017 & ISO 19011:2018 Testing and Calibration Laboratories Assessor Training
Food Safety Management (ISO 22000:2018 and FSSC 22000) | BRCGS, GMP and HACCP Trainings
ISO 9001:2015 Lead Auditor Training | Bureau Veritas
Occupational Safety (First Aid and Fire Safety), Health and Environmental Awareness Trainings
Rainforest Alliance and Chain of Custody Training | Partner Africa
Globalgap Awareness and Internal Audit Training
Lean Six Sigma Management

Referees

Mrs. Susan Kaburi

Human Resources Manager Pressmaster Africa Ltd | Nairobi 0720 466 474 hr@pressmaster.co.ke

Mrs. Caroline Rutto

Shipping and Documents Coordinator James Finlay (K) Ltd | Kericho 0722 616 642 caroline.rutto@finlays.co.ke

Mrs. Roselida Kisero

Director Larbcorpt Laboratories | Nairobi 0720 118 459 info@larbcorpt.com